Good evening.
My name is Lisa Mariello, and I'm joined here tonight by my colleagues.
I don't know if you can see in the background, CEO Bowie Bertholdt, our general counsel, Edward Fitzgerald, and Carl Lee, who is an owner partner.
And we are here to present our community outreach meeting.
And this is for kindly delivery.
And our proposed address is 86 Swan Street and Medford Mass.
I'm going to share my screen now and give you a slideshow and just answer some basic questions that you might have about what a delivery operator license looks like that we're applying for in the city of Medford.
Okay.
I'll share my screen.
Excellent.
So as I mentioned, our proposed address is 86 Swan Street in Medford, Mass.
And just a little bit about us.
So Kindly Delivery is a Massachusetts adult-use cannabis company owned and operated by a local husband and wife team.
Both of us are participants of the Cannabis Control Commission's state-designated social equity program.
Kindly is a subsidiary of vertically integrated paper crane provisions LLC, which holds a final license in outdoor cultivation.
We're nearing a final license for product manufacturing and we hold provisional licenses for indoor cultivation and retail as love well provisions, all based out of Hubbardston, Mass.
Our mission at Kindly is the following.
Kindly was founded with the mission to bring environmental responsibility, social advocacy, and a passion for providing beautiful high quality products to the delivery market so that consumers can receive and enjoy marijuana and marijuana products in the privacy of their home without ever having to leave home to receive them.
And just a brief introduction.
So as I mentioned, my name is Lisa Mariello.
I'm the vice president and co-founder of Paper Crane and its affiliates, including Kindly Delivery.
Bowie Bertold, who I introduced before.
Again, he's our CEO of Paper Crane and its affiliates.
Ed Fitzgerald Esquire is our general counsel.
He's also a Medford resident.
Carl Lee, also a Medford resident.
He serves as our general contractor and again, is an owner and partner.
Ben Sandroff is another owner partner of Paper Crane and also kindly.
He's a cultivation manager as well as providing sales and marketing support.
And so just a bit of background about Paper Crane, because to consider Kindly Delivery is also to think about how we started as Paper Crane.
And so this is, you'll see some photos here of our site.
So our Paper Crane headquarters are located in Hubbardston, Mass.
And we have a tier six outdoor cultivation, which is an organic and regenerative
sun grown cultivation site.
And so this is the condition of how we found it.
And this, these are some photos of the work in process in rehabilitating the site and turning it into the beautiful farm that it is now.
Who doesn't love a before and after?
So you can see this is our farm and it's full glory this summer with plants in the ground, almost 50,000 square feet of canopy.
And so Paper Crane will supply the bulk of Kindly's products, allowing us to offer to our customers the highest quality marijuana and marijuana products on the market with affordability, control, security, and confidence.
The ability to sell our own products will also maximize our financial contributions to the city of Medford directly via our HCA and tax benefits and also to community organizations in need of support and resources.
The delivery licenses defined by the CCC, they've been held exclusively and they were created exclusively for social equity businesses for a minimum of three years.
and the definition is the following.
A marijuana delivery operator or delivery operator means an entity licensed to purchase at wholesale and warehouse finished marijuana products acquired from a marijuana cultivator, marijuana product manufacturer, microbusiness, or craft marijuana cooperative.
and white label, sell, and deliver finished marijuana products, marijuana accessories, and marijuana branded goods directly to consumers, but is not authorized to repackage marijuana or marijuana products or operate a storefront under this license.
A delivery operator is an additional license type
which allows for limited delivery of marijuana or marijuana products to consumers and shall not be considered to be a retailer.
A delivery operator is authorized to sell finished products directly to consumers and a delivery operator shall register as a vendor with the Department of Revenue and collect and remit marijuana.
retail taxes.
In other words, the city of Medford will be entitled to the 3% local optional tax for a delivery operator, just as for dispensaries, and since kindly delivery is a social equity
business, they'll be entitled to an additional 1%.
And that's thanks to the newly passed legislation.
And so just to clarify, the above, we are not a retail store, in the sense that we will not have in a storefront, there will be no signage outside of our facility.
And so it's
basically a pretty covert operation, unless people really specifically try to search out where our headquarters are located, they really won't know, which provides a security benefit.
So the licensing and processing timeline, I included this funny video because to me it really reflects just the kind of bureaucracy and red tape that going through the licensing process really is.
And so in April of 2022, we submitted the application to the CAC and the city of Medford.
will receive our pre-certification status from the CCC as soon as I
to.
Complete this meeting, actually.
Um so the, um.
Community outreach meeting is being held currently and then following that in September will be the review and consideration of our application by the C A C formally.
In October 2022.
We hope to sign the H C A with the
In October, we'll apply for a special permit.
In December, we hope to receive our special permit.
We'll apply for the building permit, receive our building permit, and the CCC will approve our architectural review at that time as well.
Also in December, we will receive our provisional license from the CCC and we will complete our site renovation and begin to outfit the deliveries, the delivery vehicles for compliance.
In the new year, January 2023, we'll complete construction, install our top-notch security system with American Alarm, and begin hiring of local Medford residents and finalize the outfitting of our delivery vehicles.
In February, we'll receive our certificate of occupancy.
The CCC performs the post-provisional license inspection.
The following month, we'll receive our final license, begin staff training, and then in the spring, April and May of 2023, we'll begin to stock our warehouse with inventory and commence operations and deliveries will begin to customers.
Hence, the many steps and lots of paperwork that goes along with that.
Wrong direction.
Okay.
And so you might ask why delivery?
And we think it's pretty straightforward.
So delivery has become the norm for busy adults.
The COVID-19 pandemic has shined a light on how much consumers value the service of items being delivered to their doorstep.
Kindly, Delivery understands that cannabis home delivery is the next frontier in this burgeoning recreational industry.
It can be the safest option for those who might not be able to visit a retail store due to health concerns like COVID.
Although the stigma is fading, consumers value the ability to be discreet in their cannabis use and appreciate that delivery is simply the most personalized and convenient way to shop for busy adults.
Cannabis has been delivered through medical dispensaries to patients since April of 2017 with great ease, success, and without incident.
With home delivery, there is minimal risk of post-purchase public consumption.
It encourages safe private consumption at home and reduces the likelihood of impaired driving.
Home delivery can also reduce the traffic impacts and nuisances associated with dispensaries that are often concerns of abutters and residents.
We acknowledge this is often a stigmatization, but welcome the opportunity to mitigate these risks entirely.
Security is first and foremost in our operations.
So regarding the security of our warehouse, as I mentioned previously, no customers are allowed on the premises, nor will our location be made easily available to the public.
American Alarm will install our state-of-the-art security system with high-end, high-resolution Avigilon cameras, both interior and exterior.
All camera footage is stored for 90 days.
We are grateful to be in such close proximity to our neighbors, the Medford Police Department, since if there is a breach of security detected, we know they'll be there in moments.
Product is stored in a locked vault until order fulfillment.
Orders are loaded into vehicles within a secure fenced-in area.
Regarding vehicle security, products are kept in a locked compartment inside the unmarked vehicle.
Vehicles are equipped with their own security cameras.
Each vehicle is staffed with two drivers, both of whom wear body cameras and do not exit the vehicle until they're making a delivery.
And their body camera footage is stored for 90 days.
These are some photos of the site.
Note the difference.
If you're looking at the top and bottom pictures on the left-hand side, the windows have already been replaced, and there have been some great updates to the space, but we think it's gonna be really just an ideal warehouse for our fulfillment.
If you look at the larger picture on the right hand side of the screen, you can see there is a fenced in area and we will make sure that that fence stays locked when cars are not entering or exiting the site.
This is a site plan of 86 Swan Street.
There are six overnight parking spaces, two daytime employee parking spaces.
The deliveries will be received at rolling door number one.
And I can...
I think with my cursor here, I can highlight where the delivery loading will take place.
There is a secure dumpster area that is located behind the fence right here.
And behind the building, there's some space for some parking and really just, you know, a very nice flow of traffic, you know, entering and exiting the area of the site.
Minimal congestion, we don't see any issues with there being, you know, any traffic nuisances.
kindly will deliver to the cities and towns within a 10-mile radius, only where deliveries are permitted according to the CCC's municipal zoning tracker and excluding federal HUD housing, college, university housing, and non-residential establishments.
Those cities and towns include Medford, Somerville, Cambridge, Melrose, Malden, Arlington, Belmont, Watertown, Newton, and Boston.
Deliveries may only be received by the person who placed the order and with proper ID verification.
They must be at home to physically receive the package, and by proper ID verification, it would be a government-issued ID.
Like in dispensaries, there is a purchase limit of one ounce of flour or its equivalent in finished products.
To start, orders placed after 2 p.m.
will be ready for next day delivery and those placed before 2 p.m.
will be delivered same day.
In year one, we'll have four delivery vehicles and plan to expand to six in year two.
By year four, we hope to expand to 10 vehicles.
And so in order to make all of this happen, we will engage with third party technology platforms.
Dutchie is one of them.
They're an e-commerce platform customers would use to place orders via their cashless payment platform.
They're actually the largest technology platform in the cannabis space in the country.
So totally secure payment platform.
And so the customers would place their order through Deci at that point of checkout, they'll have to provide a photo of their government issued ID.
And then that technology will integrate with OnFleet.
And so OnFleet integrates and allows us to route and dispatch orders and track and communicate with drivers and customers in real time.
So all of our drivers will be able to communicate with us
and will have access to their GPS.
It's just an added security feature.
And the customers will receive a text notification when their driver is close, since it is the person that placed the order that has to be home to receive that order.
So they'll receive that notification ahead of time that their driver is nearby so that they can be ready.
Again, they'll have to provide verification and proof of delivery with a valid government issued ID for every single transaction so that this really helps to prevent any products getting into the hands of miners.
Again, security is really at the foremost of our operation.
We prioritize our hiring with Medford residents.
So we will ensure that 50% of new hires will be from Medford.
Realizing the benefits to the community that jobs offer, we will prioritize receiving Medford residents applications first and conducting interviews with those applicants before others.
Mystic Valley Area Branch NAACP has agreed to help us with our hiring needs, and so we'll partner with them to advertise for available opportunities to help facilitate our prioritization of Medford residents as well as meet our diversity goals.
I'll touch on that soon.
20 new hires within year one is what we're aiming for.
Upon our launch will expand our hiring with each year and will promote from within offering training and mentorship where applicable.
We offer competitive wages and benefits.
Benefits include paid time off, paid 12 weeks maternity leave, paid six weeks paternity leave, paid sick and family leave, health benefits, as well as an option to enroll in a 401k program.
Diversity Goals Programs and Measurements.
This is something that we take very seriously.
I'm happy to say that we have not just met, but we've exceeded our diversity goals at Paper Crane.
Kindly also will implement a diversity plan to promote equity among minorities.
women, veterans, persons with disabilities, and those falling under LGBTQ+, with 70% of those hired falling into the demographics of 25% women, 15% minorities, 10% veterans, 10% persons with disabilities, 10% persons considering themselves LGBTQ+.
So the program is that Kindly Delivery will partner with the Mystic Valley Area Branch under NAACP for recruitment needs.
And then at the end of the year, we will check in and measure our success and use the above metrics to make sure that we've met our goals.
Excuse me.
So to continue with our diversity goals.
So our next goal is promoting one individual per year, which falls into any of the demographics that we just spoke about, to positions of management and kindly delivery, or our sister companies, paper crane provisions and love will provisions where applicable.
The program is to provide two individuals per year mentoring and professional trainings and management pertaining to operating a marijuana establishment to the company employees who fall within the above demographics to prepare them for and promote them to positions of management
within Kindly Delivery or Lovewell provisions or paper crane provisions.
This training program will be open to a minimum of one employee per year.
The training program will consist of one-on-one mentoring training that will help promote different skill sets, management experience that is individualized for each employee to help them obtain management positions at the company or outside the company in another marijuana establishment.
At the end of the year, we will take a measurement, or I'm sorry, we'll hold semi-annual meetings of the Kindly Delivery Diversity Board made up of myself and one or two other female employees, preferably also falling into one of the other categories noted before, depending on our employee count, which will be named later.
The board will meet to discuss the progress of the diversity plan and to schedule community outreach
meetings and amend the plan as necessary.
Or I'm sorry, to schedule community outreach and amend the plan as necessary.
As a social equity company, we have felt the direct positive impacts of a program designed to give back and we will carry this theme of giving back to our host community throughout all that we do.
We've created a program called Kindly Contributing to optimize and monitor our charitable efforts.
We're excited about fostering close relationships with local nonprofits, organizations, and communities.
Excuse me.
Sorry communities in need.
It's a lot of reading my voice is getting dry in need of support, whether through economic charitable contributions, or, or in the form of voluntary community service like trash pickup and planting trees.
Thank you.
A unique feature of kindly contributing will include an opportunity.
at the moment of customer checkout to learn about our partner organization's missions and choose to which cause the customer would like to donate, since a portion of every sale will go towards a nonprofit organization as a charitable contribution.
This approach not only raises money directly and efficiently, but also increases awareness to many important causes.
Kindly contributing will review our plan regularly to monitor our impacts and make adjustments as necessary to optimize our program of giving.
These are some of the organizations that we've chosen.
It was not easy to choose just a handful, and I'm sure that as our company grows, we can add more to the list.
But the following are some of the local organizations that we feel are well aligned with our own mission of inclusivity, public health, the arts, support of the environment, and our youth.
And again, they are including but not limited to the following.
Medford Health Matters, Medford Educational Foundation,
And I'll just read a little bit about those two so far.
So Medford Health Matters is a community coalition that works to improve the health status and quality of life for people who live or work in Medford.
They strive to incorporate concerns about the environment into a healthy lifestyle, hold an annual walkathon, provide linkages and information for Medford residents to existing services for social and emotional support and emotional disorders, treatment, prevent substance abuse,
and they have a Youth Advisory Council, also known as Teens Against Drinking and Drugs.
Medford Educational Foundation is a nonprofit foundation committed to supporting innovation and excellence in the Medford public schools.
Their goal is to enhance educational opportunities for all Medford students by investing in classroom enrichment and professional development to support innovative teaching.
Medford sorry trees Medford is a local citizen advocacy group dedicated to sustaining and enhancing Medford's tree canopy.
Trees Medford supports the city's tree wardens work and advocates for tree planting and tree maintenance projects.
We love that this organization is not only contributing positively to the environment and beautifying Medford in the process, but it's also creating equity for its residents by planting trees in lower income neighborhoods, which historically have fewer trees and overall less canopy.
And we really loved this organization since it has that kind of dual mission of enhancing Medford's tree canopy and promoting sustainability in the city, but also that it's helping to create equity by beautifying the lower income neighborhoods across the city.
And CACHE, another beloved organization, the Coalition of Arts, Culture, and a Healthy Economy.
CACHE in Medford is a nonprofit organization made up of a coalition of over 20 different cultural institutions in Medford, collectively advocating for the arts in Medford and working together to make the community a more vibrant place.
This coalition was founded in 2010 as a way to bring diverse cultural organizations of Medford together and has quickly grown from five organizations to 20, including Circle the Square and the Mystic River Celebration.
CACHE maintains Arts Across Medford, an online calendar of arts and culture events in Medford, featuring nearly 1000 events each year.
We are really proud that we are able to make very generous and robust financial contributions to the city of Medford.
We estimate that our financial contributions of both HCA payments and local taxes will be near six million in just the first five years.
Touching again on what I mentioned earlier, since we are a social equity business, the city of Medford is entitled to 4%
of revenue from the state because of the sweeping changes that have been passed and signed just this week by Governor Baker.
So in just year one with four delivery vehicles, we have estimated that our total payments to the city of Medford
will be near 500,000.
That number jumps to over 700,000 as we expand to six vehicles in year two.
In year three, with 10 vehicles, we surpass a million dollars in contributions.
In year four, we'll have expanded to 12 delivery vehicles, and we'll be nearing the
$1.5 million mark and then in year five with 16 delivery vehicles will have quite a fleet and will be able to contribute near $2 million.
And so that is just in the first five years.
Sustainability is really at the heart of our operation, both at Paper Crane and with Kindly Delivery as well.
So it's, so I'll just go back up and read.
So sustainability is at the forefront of our operations at both kindly delivery and our primary source for providing marijuana, our own cultivation facility paper crane provisions.
As an outdoor or sun-grown cultivator, we have made a direct pivot away from the energy-costly practices of cultivating marijuana indoors.
Instead, we cultivate on a beautiful, sun-filled, rain-watered, agricultural-style farm, setting ourselves apart from an industry which generally utilizes high-energy, high-pressure sodium light bulbs,
extensive HVAC and watering systems, which are all energy inefficient.
Kindly will also be an energy efficient operation.
As a delivery service, we know that the best way that we can support the environment is by committing to the use of fuel efficient vehicles, hybrid or completely electric cars.
We make a promise to utilize the most eco-friendly option reasonable and are currently researching the best option for our first small fleet.
Some cars that we've considered are the Toyota RAV4 hybrid, just as an example, or a Prius.
So something in like a small SUV range or a hatchback would work well.
We will ensure that there's no idling when performing deliveries.
Our delivery agents will be trained to turn off their vehicles while making stops at customers' residences for delivery.
Our Medford warehouse will use only LED lights and incorporate energy-saving practices wherever possible.
We will offer water-filling stations to our employees to discourage the use of single plastic.
We will have separate trash and recycling stations and encourage the use of recycled and compostable products for things such as office supplies and food product wrappers.
Kindly, we'll seek out other eco-friendly companies whose environmentally sustainable values are aligned with ours to purchase marijuana and marijuana products to be sold that are not provided by paper crane provisions.
That concludes our slideshow.
This slide has my contact information.
This is my email address printed there, and that is my phone number.
I welcome any members of the community, any city officials who have any questions to please feel free to reach out.
My line is open.
I'd love to dive in deeper with any further questions, provide SOPs, just quell any concerns that you might have.
And I thank you all for watching.
Okay.
Nobody has actually joined.
So I think at this time, I'll just stop.
Stop.
Okay.